Hello, my name is Gemma Hurley.
I'm a senior lecturer at Kingston University and St George's University of London.
I'm also a nurse practitioner where health history forms a key part of my role.
History taking forms the cornerstone of patient health assessment and so I would like to take you through the core principles of history taking.
To do that, I'm going to bring in a patient and demonstrate the key steps involved in history taking.
Come on in and have a seat.
Thank you.
Hi, my name is Gemma Hurley.
I'm a nurse practitioner and you are?
Paul Collins.
Okay, Mr. Collins, how would you like me to call you?
Paul's fine.
Is that okay?
All right.
Well, for me to be able to help you today, I need to take a history which will involve me asking you questions about your health and also about your social circumstances.
Is that okay with you?
It's fine.
OK.
Before we start, I just wanted to confirm your details.
So, it's Paul Collins and you're 46 years old.
And is this your address?
That's right.
Perfect.
Great.
OK.
Excellent.
So, how can I help you today?
Well, I've had a cough for a few days.
It's just driving me nuts, really.
Right, how long has the cough been there for?
I suppose about 3 or 4 days now.
Has it?
And have you got any other symptoms with that cough?
I've got quite a sore throat, that's quite bad as well.
Right, and a sore throat, has it been there the same amount of time?
Yes, yeah, they're both pretty much the same time.
Gosh, okay.
And the cough and sore throat, is it worse any particular time of the day or night?
Well, cough's probably worse.
first thing in the morning, I notice it particularly when I get up, sore throat's there all the time really.
Is it?
Are you able to swallow with that sore throat?
Yes.
You can, you can drink.
OK.
And the cough, can you describe it for me?
It's just a fairly meaty cough, you know, all sorts of muck really.
Right, OK.
What colour is the muck that you're coughing up?
Green really.
Is it large amounts or?
A fair amount.
Is it?
Is there any blood in it?
No, I haven't seen any blood.
Okay.
And how bad on a scale of nought to ten is that cough for you?
Ten being the worst possible.
I suppose it's about 6 or 7 really.
Right.
And is there any area in your throat or anywhere in your chest that's painful?
Well, I mean, my throat and neck are sore when I cough.
Right.
But other than that, no, it's just the sore throat.
Okay.
Does it travel anywhere else, this sore throat?
Any sort of radiation of pain?
No, no.
Okay.
And has any other persons been affected by this?
Have they been sort of coughing around you, been in contact with anyone?
Well, my girlfriend, she had a cough last week.
Has she?
Okay.
And has she been well in the cell for?
She was ill for a few days.
Has she?
Okay.
But she's better now.
What makes a cough and a sore throat better for you?
Is there any relieving factors?
Well, a cough, nothing really.
You know, I've tried over-the-counter sort of stuff from the chemist and that didn't work.
It didn't help?
The throat, if I have a warm drink, that helps.
Okay, okay.
Anything make it worse at all, this cough?
No, not really.
Nothing at all.
Okay.
What do you think it is?
I don't know.
I just think I need some antibiotics.
Right.
Okay.
I just want to ask you more specific questions now.
You said there's no blood in the phlegm, but is there any fever, any feeling shivery?
The first day I was ill I was a bit shaky like that but now I'm not.
Okay and what about breathlessness?
So you've got any breathing problem or chest tightness?
No.
Nothing at all.
Okay and when you go to bed at night are you able to lie on your same amount of pillows?
Yes.
You are.
Okay and what about, are you feeling, because I know you're coughing up lots of green phlegm, is any dripping at the back of your throat at all?
No.
Nothing like that, okay.
And have you had any unexplained weight loss at all?
No, none at all.
Good.
Any recent travel abroad?
for months.
Okay, okay.
I just want to go through some of your key sort of body systems, Paul, just to find out about your overall health.
Can you tell me about, have you suffered headaches at all?
Sometimes I get headaches.
Do you?
Okay.
How often do you get headaches?
Once every month, something like that.
Is it?
And have you seen your doctor for that?
No, I just take some painkillers and they go away.
They go away.
Okay.
Have you ever had any head injuries?
No.
Okay.
Good.
And what about your vision?
Do you wear glasses?
No.
Okay.
Vision's good?
Yeah.
Okay.
Do you ever suffer with nasal congestion or?
Sinus problems?
The only time I do is with cats really.
They set me off.
Are you allergic to cats?
I think I must be.
What about your tastes?
Any change in taste?
No.
Do you get mouth ulcers at all?
Sometimes I do.
Do you?
If I'm busy at work or something, sometimes I get mouth ulcers.
Okay, and you have a sore throat now, but do you get recurrent sore throats?
No.
You don't?
Years.
Good, good.
And any sort of problems with your chest in terms of heart problems, breathing problems?
No, nothing that.
And your bowels working all right?
They're fine.
Good.
Waterworks okay?
Yeah.
Excellent.
I hope you don't mind, but could I just ask a little bit about your sexual history?
Are you in a relationship?
Yeah.
Okay.
Are you heterosexual or gay?
Yeah.
Okay.
And contraception?
Do you use barrier methods?
I work with my girlfriends on the pill.
Okay.
And it's a long-term relationship, I said?
Yeah, it's been for a few years.
Okay.
And what about your bones?
Any joint problems?
Well, you're sort of aches and pains if you've been busy at work, but no, not really.
Okay, good.
Okay, and how's your mood?
How do you feel in yourself?
Fed up at the moment.
Normally good, but I just want to get rid of this cough.
The cough, okay, but no sleeping problems and feeling low moods in terms of No, no, no.
Good, excellent.
A little bit about your surgical in the past.
Have you ever had any operations?
I had an operation, it must be 20 years ago, some sort of operation on my back.
Ah, right.
Do you remember, recall?
It was a, a pie something, pilo.
Pilonidal sinus.
That's the one.
Okay, okay.
And has it been alright since then?
Yeah, no problems at all.
Okay.
And no other operations?
I'm just going to list off, just to probe your mind a bit, in terms of medical history, have you or any of your first degree relatives, so mum, dad, siblings, ever suffered with any jaundice where you've seen yourself go yellow?
No.
Okay.
Any anaemia at all?
Iron deficiency?
No, no.
Good.
Okay, have you ever had a heart attack or any member of your family?
No.
Okay.
What about TB?
Anybody with TB or you've been No, not as far as I know.
Good.
Any thyroid problems?
No.
Okay.
Any rheumatic fever or rheumatoid arthritis?
No.
Good.
Okay.
Any heart problems?
No.
Okay, any high blood pressure?
Well, I've got high blood pressure.
Oh, you have?
Okay.
And when was that diagnosed for?
That was diagnosed, what, 2 years ago now?
Was it?
And is it well controlled?
Well, I go, yeah, I think so.
I go to the doctor regularly and have my blood pressure checked.
It seems okay.
Perfect.
When was it last checked?
It was last checked about 2 weeks ago.
And everything was great?
Yeah, I think so.
Perfect.
It was okay.
Okay.
And what about diabetes?
Do you have any diabetes?
Yes, yes.
Or you do?
Yes, I'm diabetic.
Right.
And do you know what type?
It's the one with the tablet.
Okay, so you take tablets.
I do.
Okay, when were you diagnosed with diabetes?
That was about 3 years ago now.
Okay, and when was your last check-up for your diabetes?
I had that at the same time as I had my blood pressure.
Perfect, and they were happy?
Yeah.
Okay, perfect.
Any asthma at all?
No.
Okay, any strokes?
You had any many sort of numbness or family members?
No, my dad died 2 years ago with a stroke.
How old was he?
He was 72.
72.
Okay, and any cancers in the family or you've been?
Okay, good.
Okay.
Brilliant.
I just want to move you along a bit further.
Do you take any prescribed medicines?
I know that you've got diabetes and high blood pressure.
I do.
I take Ramipril.
Okay.
And I take netformin and there's another one that begins with G for the diabetes.
Glycozide.
Excellent.
Okay.
And do you know the dosage of the Ramipril?
I think it's 5 milligrams.
5 milligrams.
And do you take it regularly?
Oh yeah, yeah.
Good.
I take it every evening.
And no side effects with it?
I did have an awful cough to start with but that's stopped now.
It's settled, good.
Okay and do you know the metformin?
Do you take it, do you do it in a dosage and how often?
I take it 3 times a day but I don't know what dose that is.
Okay, we can check that out.
We can follow that up.
Okay.
And what about allergies?
Are you allergic to anything?
Well, the only thing I think I'm allergic to is cats, but no one's ever told me that.
Okay, so that's the environment.
Do you know if you've got any drug allergies?
No, no, I don't think so.
And any foods like nut allergy or anything like that?
No.
Okay, perfect, good.
Okay, I need to ask you this.
Do you take any recreational drugs at all?
No, I don't have anything to do with them.
Excellent, good.
Any over-the-counter, you said you've been to?
Well, I had some cough medicine.
Okay.
And have you had paracetamol recently?
I had it a few days ago for the sore throat which it helped a bit.
It helped a little bit.
Okay.
And do you do any herbal remedies at all?
Nothing at all.
Excellent.
That's brilliant.
Okay.
Well, a little bit about your social background, if you don't mind me asking.
What's your occupation?
I'm a builder.
Right, okay.
And have you been lately exposed to dust or any sort of new substances?
No, no, so it's a fairly standard new build at the moment.
Okay, and you're happy with work?
plenty of work at the moment, so that's good.
Great, excellent.
And what about, you said you've got a girlfriend, do you live with her?
I do.
Right, okay.
And you're happy, everything's good at home?
Yeah, it's fine.
No stresses?
No, no.
Excellent, okay.
And do you live in a house or a flat or?
It's a 2bed house.
It's a 2bedroom house.
Are you a house owner, are you?
Yes.
You own your own house.
Excellent.
Good.
Can I ask you, do you smoke at all?
Yeah, I do smoke.
Do you?
OK.
Can I ask what you smoke?
I just smoke cigarettes, low tar cigarettes.
Low tar.
And how many cigarettes do you go through in a day?
Well, it's about 3 packs.
About 2 packs every 3 days.
Is it?
Okay.
And at what age did you start smoking?
It would have been about 30.
Age 30.
Okay.
Have you thought about giving up?
Well, not really, not at the moment.
You don't want to consider that at the moment?
No, no.
Okay.
Well, when you do, we're here any time.
We've got lots of support strategies in place, so whenever you feel you would like to talk about stopping smoking, we're here just to let you know, okay?
I just want to ask you about your alcohol intake.
Do you drink?
I do drink, yeah.
OK.
What do you normally drink?
Wine.
OK.
And how much wine do you drink?
Not a lot really.
A couple of glasses a week.
In the week?
Yeah.
Not a lot at all really.
OK.
Good.
And your diet?
Do you eat well?
Yeah.
No, we eat really well.
My girlfriend's, you know, really into healthy eating so we grow our own vegetables at home.
Wonderful.
Excellent.
Great.
And do you exercise?
Not really, because I'm just on site so much, I'm busy all day, I'm very active during the day, but I don't really exercise outside.
Right.
I suppose if you could find that time, it would be relaxing, I suppose, to help, you know, good for your diabetes as well, if we could.
I just want to sum up, Paul, if you don't mind.
Please correct me if I've got any of it wrong.
You've had this cough and sore throat for the last 3 days.
Nothing makes it really better, or you have taken your paracetamol.
That's helped a little bit.
You've not had any blood in that phlegm, no fever, no unexplained weight loss.
Breathing's okay as well.
You've got type 2 diabetes because you take tablets for that and it's well controlled and so is your blood pressure.
Your dad died sadly of a stroke.
You live with your girlfriend and you're quite happy.
Work is good and you just really want us to sort out your sore throat and cough.
Yes, please.
Okay, okay.
Is there anything else you want to add to that before we move on?
No, no, that's it I think.
Alright, okay.
Well, what we need to do now is to check some vital signs and I need to examine you before we could decide, you know, what's going on with your sore throat and cough and take it from there.
Is that okay with you?
fine.
Good, thank you.
Well that concludes our demonstration of the history taking process.
Paul is a senior lecturer at the University and has kindly offered to give feedback from a patient perspective.
The key principles used in the history taking process was first and foremost me as the practitioner ensuring that the environment was safe and accessible for the patient.
I was also mindful to avoid interruptions thus maintaining the patient's privacy and confidentiality.
As I called a patient in I was mindful not to use the patient's first name but to seek permission.
So how did you feel about that Paul?
I thought that was quite appropriate and I felt that you respected my right to be called Mr Collins or Paul accordingly and I was happy to be called Paul.
Great.
I also felt it was imperative that I gained informed consent and so I told the patient at the outset what was to be expected and seeked consent from him.
I also thought that it was important that I used an open-ended question at the outset so that the patient could tell his story in his own words.
How did you find that?
I thought that was good and I certainly had the opportunity to talk about what was concerning me which was obviously the cough.
So yeah, I got that out of the way quite quickly I think.
Great, all good.
The other thing is although I'm wanting the patient to tell their own story, I also am mindful of the red flags, thus ruling out life-threatening causes.
I tried to be systematic but I also wanted to respond to the patient's cues as well.
And so whenever the patient gave a leading answer, I would allow him the scope to explore that further.
I then went through the key processes of history taking and then allowed at the very end to sum up, thus allowing the patient to clarify from their perspective.
I was mindful as well not to use jargons but how did you feel because sometimes we get lost as practitioners and we see medical jargons as normal terminology.
I think on the whole it was very good and for the most part it was fairly free of medical jargon although I know at 1 point you did ask about social history which I think had the potential to confuse somebody
Of course, I didn't think of it like that, but that's so right.
Absolutely.
I mean, the questions, once you'd said you were going to ask about the social history, I think the questions were absolutely fine.
It's just that headlining really of that particular area of history taking, perhaps.
and that's important for me to note as a practitioner.
Well, that concludes the key steps in history taking process and we hope that we've helped you to add structure and depth to your history taking in the clinical setting.
And I will put some referencing online for you that will help you to explore further the key issues surrounding history taking.
Thank you very much.