Good morning Mr. Thompson, I'm Dr. Ramirez. I need to take a full medical history from you today — is that alright?
Yes, that's absolutely fine, go ahead.
Can you tell me what brings you in today? What's the main problem?
I've had crushing chest pain for about three hours, and it's radiating down my left arm into my jaw.
On a scale of zero to ten, how severe is the pain right now?
It's an eight out of ten, maybe a nine when it's at its worst.
When did it start, and was there anything that triggered it?
It started about three hours ago while I was climbing the stairs at work. It came on suddenly.
Are there any associated symptoms — shortness of breath, nausea, sweating?
Yes, I've been short of breath, I feel nauseated, and I'm sweating quite a lot — diaphoretic.
Do you have any allergies to medications or foods?
I'm allergic to Penicillin — it gives me a severe rash and hives.
What medications are you currently taking?
I take Metformin 500 milligrams twice daily for my type 2 diabetes.
I'm also on Lisinopril 10 milligrams once a day for high blood pressure.
And Atorvastatin 40 milligrams at bedtime for cholesterol.
Any past medical history I should know about?
I was diagnosed with type 2 diabetes about three years ago.
I've had essential hypertension for about five years now.
High cholesterol, diagnosed about two years ago.
Any previous surgeries or hospital stays?
I had an appendectomy back in 2010 — no complications, straightforward.
I also had a right knee arthroscopy in 2018.
What about your family medical history?
My father had a heart attack at 52 and also has type 2 diabetes.
My mother has hypertension, and she had breast cancer but she's in remission.
My brother has type 2 diabetes as well, diagnosed at 45.
When was your last flu shot and Covid booster?
I got the flu vaccine about a month ago, right arm, lot number was 4AB23.
Covid booster was three months ago, I think it was Pfizer.
Tetanus booster five years ago.
Do you smoke or drink alcohol?
I quit smoking five years ago. I used to smoke a pack a day for about twenty years.
I drink alcohol socially — a beer or two on weekends.
What do you do for work, and what's your living situation?
I work as a construction foreman. I live with my wife in a single-family home.
Let me review some point-of-care labs. Your last HbA1c was 7.2 percent about two weeks ago.
Fasting glucose was 140 milligrams per deciliter at that visit.
You're doing daily self-monitoring of blood glucose — glad to hear that.
Your last HIV screening came back negative.
Syphilis screening was non-reactive.
Okay, let me take your vital signs now. Blood pressure is 165 over 95.
Heart rate is 108 beats per minute and regular.
Temperature is 98.6 degrees Fahrenheit.
Oxygen saturation is 96 percent on room air.
You're six feet tall and weigh 210 pounds today.
That puts your BMI at approximately 28.5.
On physical exam — patient appears diaphoretic and in moderate distress.
HEENT: pupils equal, round, reactive to light. No jugular venous distension.
Neck: supple, no lymphadenopathy, thyroid normal to palpation.
Cardiovascular: tachycardic, regular rhythm, S1 and S2 present, no murmurs, rubs, or gallops.
Lungs: clear to auscultation bilaterally, no wheezes or crackles.
Abdomen: soft, non-tender, no masses or organomegaly, bowel sounds active.
Musculoskeletal: full range of motion in all extremities, no edema.
Neurologic: alert and oriented times three, cranial nerves two through twelve intact.
Skin: diaphoretic, no rashes, no lesions, good turgor.
Psychological: anxious but cooperative, appropriate affect, no suicidal ideation.
My primary assessment is acute coronary syndrome, rule out STEMI — ICD-10 I20.0.
Secondary diagnosis: poorly controlled type 2 diabetes, ICD-10 E11.65.
Also essential hypertension, ICD-10 I10.
Plan: Order a stat 12-lead EKG and troponin I, repeat in three hours.
Order chest X-ray and complete blood count, basic metabolic panel.
Start aspirin 325 milligrams chewed now.
Sublingual nitroglycerin 0.4 milligrams as needed for chest pain.
Admit for cardiac monitoring and cardiology consultation.
Follow-up with cardiology in 48 hours after discharge.
Patient education: discussed warning signs of heart attack, low-sodium diet, and smoking cessation reinforced.
Care coordination: referral placed to cardiology and diabetes educator.